Chase Stokes

cstokes@ischool.berkeley.edu chasejstokes.github.io

I am a mixed methods researcher situated at the intersection of language and visualization. My work focuses on the challenges and opportunities presented by multimodal information displays, examining how language shapes readers' experiences and understandings of visualized data. I aim to identify best practices for integrating text and visualizations and improve the effectiveness of information communication.

EDUCATION

PhD. in Information Science

2021 – present

University of California at Berkeley

Advisor: Marti Hearst, PhD.

Relevant coursework: HCI Research, UX Research, Information

Visualization and Presentation, Interface Aesthetics

B.A. in Psychology and Gender and Sexuality Studies

2021

Northwestern University, GPA 3.92 Advisor: Steven Franconeri, PhD.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Graduate Student Researcher

2021 – present

Hearst Lab, UC Berkeley

Temporary Research Assistant

Summer 2024

Northeastern University, Khoury College

Research Intern

Summer 2023

Tableau

Undergraduate Research Assistant

2018 - 2021

Visual Thinking Lab, Northwestern University

Data Collector Summer 2021

Couple and Family Development Lab, The Family Institute at Northwestern University

Undergraduate Research Assistant

2019 - 2021

Couple and Family Development Lab, The Family Institute at Northwestern University

Undergraduate Summer Intern

Summer 2019

Couple and Family Development Lab, The Family Institute at Northwestern University

PUBLICATIONS

- **Stokes, C.,** & Hearst, M.A. (2024). "It's a Good Idea to Put It Into Words": Writing `Rudders' in the Initial Stages of Visualization Design. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- **Stokes, C.,** Sanker, C., Cogley, B., & Setlur, V. (2024). From Delays to Densities: Exploring Uncertainty through Speech, Text, and Visualization. Computer Graphics Forum.
- **Stokes, C.,** Sanker, C., Cogley, B., & Setlur, V. (2024). Mixing Modes: Active and Passive Integration of Speech, Text, and Visualization for Communicating Data Uncertainty. Computer Graphics Forum.
- **Stokes, C.,** Bearfield, C. X., & Hearst, M.A. (2023). The Role of Text in Visualizations: How Annotations Shape Perceptions of Bias and Influence Predictions. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- Bearfield, C. X., **Stokes, C.,** Lovett, A., & Franconeri, S. (2023). What Does the Chart Say? Grouping Cues Guide Viewer Comparisons and Conclusions in Bar Charts. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- **Stokes, C.,** Setlur, V., Cogley, B., Satyanarayan, A., and Hearst, M.A. (2022). Striking a Balance: Reader Takeaways and Preferences when Integrating Text and Charts. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- Xiong, C., **Stokes, C.**, Kim, Y. S., & Franconeri, S. (2022). Seeing What You Believe or Believing What You See? Belief Biases Correlation Estimation. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.

WORKSHOP PAPERS

- **Stokes, C.,** and Hearst, M.A. (2022). Why More Text is (Often) Better: Themes from Reader Preferences for Integration of Charts and Text, NLVIZ Workshop, IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- **Stokes, C.,** and Hearst, M.A. (2021). Give Text A Chance: Advocating for Equal Consideration for Language and Visualization, NLVIZ Workshop, IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.

POSTERS AND PRESENTATIONS

- **Stokes, C**. (2024). Combining Text and Visuals for Effective Data Communication. Presentation at the Doctoral Colloquium at IEEE VIS Conference 2024.
- **Stokes, C.,** Xiong, C., & Hearst, M.A. (2022, Nov). Driving Reader Interpretations with Text Annotations in Data Visualizations. Poster presented at Society for Judgement and Decision Making, San Diego, CA.
- Xiong, C., **Stokes, C.,** Lovett, A., & Franconeri, S. (2021, May). Visual Salience and Grouping Cues Guide Relation Perception in Visual Data Displays. Poster presented at Virtual Vision Sciences Society.
- **Stokes, C.,** Xiong, C., & Franconeri, S. (2020, May). Seeing What You Want: Prior Belief Biases Perception of Correlation in Scatterplots. Poster presented at Virtual 32nd APS Annual Convention, Chicago, IL.

Callahan, C., **Stokes, C.,** & Lawrence, E. (2020, May). Modifying the Relationship Quality Interview for Sexual and Gender Minority Couples. Accepted Poster Presentation at the 8th Annual LGBTQ Research Symposium at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. (Conference Canceled)

| 7 | |
|---|------------------------|
| FELLOWSHIPS, AWARDS, AND HONORS | |
| Fellowships NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program Recipient Ford Foundation Predoctoral Fellowship Honorable Mention | 2023 – present 2023 |
| School of Information Fellowship for Doctoral Study | 2021 – 2022 |
| Awards | |
| National Merit Finalist | 2017 – 2021 |
| Honors | |
| Departmental Honors - Psychology | 2021 |
| Phi Beta Kappa Northwestern University Dean's List with Distinction | 2021 2017 – 2021 |
| GRANTS | |
| Northwestern Summer Undergraduate Research Grant (\$3,500) Visual Grouping Affords Different Comparison Patterns in Visualized Data | Summer 2020 |
| Northwestern Academic Year Research Grant (\$1,000) Variations in Conclusions Afforded by Chart Type | 2020 |
| STUDENT LEADERSHIP ROLES | |
| Underrepresented Applicant Feedback Program | 2023 |
| Co-coordinated initiative to provide feedback to underrepresented PhD. ap | pplicants |
| NorCal Visualization Group Organizer Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars | 2022 – 2023 |
| Trainings Chair Masculinity, Allyship, Reflection, and Solidarity (M.A.R.S.) | 2019 – 2020 |
| Mascailing, Anyship, Renection, and Solidarity (M.A.R.S.) | |
| Participant Coordinator, | 2019 – 2020 |
| Pre-Orientation Program Coordinator Alternative Student Breaks (A.S.B.) | 2018 – 2019 |
| Programming Committee | 2018 – 2019 |
| Rainbow Alliance | |

STUDENT MEMBERSHIPS

| Association for Computing Machinery, Student Member Psychonomic Society, Student Member Cognitive Science Society, Student Member | 2021 – present 2021 – present 2021 – present |
|---|--|
| Society for Judgment and Decision Making, Student Member | 2021 – present |
| AD-HOC REVIEWS | |
| Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (TVCG) | 2023 - 2024 |
| ACM Computer-Human Interaction (CHI) | 2022 - 2024 |
| Ocean and Coastal Research | 2023 |
| Journal of Official Statistics | 2023 |
| IEEE VIS Short Papers | 2022 |
| Creativity & Cognition | 2021 |
| SERVICE AND OUTREACH | |
| 25th Anniversary of the Master of Information Management and Systems Facilitated two 30-minute panels | 2022 |
| PhD. Applicant Feedback Program Provided feedback to underrepresented applicants | 2022 - 2023 |
| Student Volunteer at IEEE VIS | 2022 |
| Washington University School of Medicine Mini-Medical School Panelist | 2019, 2021 |
| Alternative Student Breaks | 2017 – 2019 |
| College Mentors for Kids | 2017 – 2019 |

REFERENCES PROVIDED UPON REQUEST